All right. One of the things you might
want to do with an array is you might
want to sort it. Here we have a list of
six numbers. Four, five, six, 1 2 3. And
you might want to sort them into order
where it goes 1 2 3 4 5 6. And so if I
were to ask you how to do that, you
would probably look at this and just
say, "Well, duh. Move the 1 2 3 in front
of the 456 and we're done." Um, and
while that works great, unfortunately
that's not the way a computer thinks
about this. Because you see a computer
when it looks at an array, all it knows
is that it has six boxes. It doesn't
know what's inside of those boxes. It
just has six boxes. So if we wanted to
sort them, we would have to open up each
box and see what's inside of it. So the
one I'm going to show you today is
called a bubble sort. So if you look the
reason we call it bubble sort is because
we sort until the first position has
been solved and we put the smallest
thing first meaning it has bubbled all
the way up to the top and then we sort
the next position and the next position
and the next position and so on and so
forth until we've completed the bubble
sort. So just to show you this in
practice, um what we would do is we'd
open up the box in the first position.
With arrays, this is called position
zero or index zero. So if we want to
look at what's in index zero and then
the second box right here, which is
index one, we can do that. So we'll open
them up and we'll compare four and five.
If we are trying to put the smallest
item first, then we are always going to
be looking to see if we need to swap the
two things positions. So the pos the
item in position zero is four. The item
in position one is five. Five is bigger
than four. So we'll just leave things
be. We'll put the box back and then
we'll open up the box in position two.
Um so position zero and position two get
compared. Position two still has a
bigger number. So we're going to leave
things be. We'll put the box back and
open up position three. So, just again
for those of you who are less
comfortable counting with arrays, four
is in the zero position. Um, according
to a computer, we don't know what's in
five. We do know what's in sorry, four
is in the zero position. We don't know
what's in position one. We do know that
six is in position two for now. Um, but
we're going to close position two and
look at position three. So, we close
that box and open up the next box. Okay,
so four is in the zero position. One is
in the three position.
One is smaller than four. So we need to
swap these. So we're going to take one
out of the fourth or sorry out of the
third position or index three and we're
going to take four out of index zero and
we're going to swap them. So we've now
swapped them. So one has moved to the
front. And now what's in box the fourth
box or index number three is the number
four. We'll put the box back down. And
now we'll compare index 0 to index 4.
One is smaller than two. So nothing
needs to swap. We'll put our boxes down.
Compare index 0 to index 5. And one is
still smaller than three. Which means we
can put our box back down. If you're
paying attention, that means that we
have now compared index zero to every
single number here. And we know for a
fact that index 0 is the smallest one.
The one bubbled all the way up to the
front. And now that we know the first
position or index zero has been solved,
we don't even need to look at it
anymore. We can just start looking at
the second position. From here on out,
I'm going to refer to them by 1 2 3 4 5
6 so that I don't get myself tongue
twisted. But just remember that a
computer refers to them as zero, one,
two, three, four, and five. Okay, so
we're looking at the box. We're looking
at box number two, and we need to sort
it so that the next smallest number goes
into box number two. So we'll look at
box number two, and we'll compare it to
box number three. Box number two holds a
smaller number, so we won't do anything.
We'll put back down box number three and
open up box number four. We're comparing
box number two and box number four. Box
number four contains a smaller number.
So, we're going to swap them places.
Then, we're going to close box number
four and we're going to compare box
number two to box number five. Four and
two, two is smaller, so we need to swap
them. So, we're going to swap them and
we're going to move the four into box
number five and the two into box number
two. Now that we've swapped them, we'll
put back down the box on box number five
and we'll compare box number two to box
number six. So you can see there's no
need to swap these because box number
two is the smaller number. If you're
still hanging in there with me, that
means we have successfully sorted the
first two positions and we no longer
need to look at them anymore. So now
we're going to look at position number
or box number three. Box number one and
box number two have successfully bubbled
up. Okay, we'll put our boxes back down.
We'll open up box number, box number
three, and compare it to box number
four. Box number four is smaller, so we
need to swap those places. We'll put
down box number four and compare box
number three to box number five. Box
number five contains a smaller number.
So, we need to switch boxes the contents
of boxes three and five. We'll swap
those places and we'll put the box back
down on number five. Now, we compare box
three to box six. Box six contains a
smaller number, so we need to sort
switch the contents of box three and box
six. Now that we've done that, we'll put
the box back down on four. And those
astute of you may have noticed that we
have now successfully sorted our first
three positions, which means we don't
even need to look at them anymore. And
we just need to look at box four. So
we'll put our boxes back down. We'll
compare four and five. They need to
switch. We'll put the box back down and
compare four and six. Four and six need
to switch. So we'll swap them. Now, you
may have noticed we have successfully um
filled out the first four numbers,
which means we don't need to look at
them anymore. Now, we just need to look
at this slot. So, we'll put our boxes
back down. We'll compare box five and
box six. They need to swap. As soon as
we make this swap, we know that we will
have successfully sorted the first five
numbers. If you've successfully sorted
the first five numbers, then it means
that the sixth number has to be in the
right spot. So, we'll make the swap and
we are done. And that is how a bubble
sort works. Hopefully, that visual was
helpful. In the next video, we're going
to talk about how we would implement
that in